Berard Haile papers, 1893-1961 (bulk 1925-1961)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series X: Navajo Language and Grammar
  - "A List of Navaho Stems," compiled by E. Sapir. Typescript (carbon) with holograph annotations by Fr. Berard. (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - "An Introduction to Navaho," by Fr. Berard and E. Sapir. Holograph ms. by Sapir, and typescript (original). (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - "Grammatical Notes on the Navaho Language." Mimeographed. (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Verb Stems. (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Nouns, Pronouns, Adjectives. (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Verbs. (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous and fragmentary material. (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Series XI: Original Drawings and Two Drafts of the Emergence Myth
  - Many of the drawings and sketches are for published works, such as the Ethnological Dictionary and Starlore. Others unidentified. (Box 28)
  - One of the Emergence Myth drafts is a holograph manuscript, and the other a typescript (original) with holograph corrections. (Box 28)
- Series XII: Linguistic Notes (Navajo)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 29)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 30)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 31)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 32)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 33)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 34)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 35)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 36)
  - Grammar and vocabulary, in holograph and typescript, on 6 x 4 slips, arranged by Fr. Berard. Includes also some notes on Navajo culture and ceremonials. (Box 37)
- Series XIII: Index to notes for BLESSINGWAY
  - Typescript on 6 x 4 slips, compiled and arranged by Fr. Berard. Some additional holograph notes. (Box 38)
  - Typescript on 6 x 4 slips, compiled and arranged by Fr. Berard. Some additional holograph notes. (Box 39)
- Series XIV: Sand paintings
  - Fifteen large original drawings of sand paintings relating to cermonials, including MountainWay, Mountain Chant, Night Chant, Plume Way, and Naatobeca. Slides of drawings are also present.